<chapter id="miscellaneous" xreflabel="Miscellaneous Changes">

  <title>Other Changes in AspectJ 5</title>
  
  <sect1 id="pointcuts-change">
      <title>Pointcuts</title>
      
          <para>
           AspectJ 5 is more liberal than AspectJ 1.2.1 in accepting pointcut expressions
           that bind context variables in more than one location. For example, AspectJ
           1.2.1 does not allow:
           </para>

       	<programlisting><![CDATA[
       	pointcut foo(Foo foo) : (execution(* *(..)) && this(foo) ) ||
       	                                (set(* *) && target(foo));
		]]></programlisting>
		
		 <para>
		     whereas this expression is permitted in AspectJ 5. Each context variable must
		     be bound exactly once in each branch of a disjunction, and the disjunctive branches
		     must be mutually exclusive. In the above example for instance, no join point
		     can be both an execution join point and a set join point so the two branches
		     are mutually exclusive.
		  </para>
           
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="declare-soft-change">
      <title>Declare Soft</title>
      <para>
          The semantics of the <literal>declare soft</literal> statement have been 
          refined in AspectJ 5 to only soften exceptions that are not already runtime 
          exceptions. If the exception type specified in a declare soft statement is <literal>RuntimeException</literal>
          or a subtype of <literal>RuntimeException</literal> then a new XLint warning will be issued:</para>
    
       	<programlisting><![CDATA[
       	  declare soft : SomeRuntimeException : execution(* *(..));
       	  
       	  >> "SomeRuntimeException will not be softened as it is already a RuntimeException" [XLint:runtimeExceptionNotSoftened]
		]]></programlisting>
	
	   <para>
	       This XLint message can be controlled by setting the <literal>runtimeExceptionNotSoftened</literal> XLint parameter.
 	   </para>
	
	   <para>
	      If the exception type specified in a declare soft statement is a super type of <literal>RuntimeException</literal>
	      (such as <literal>Exception</literal> for example) then any <emphasis>checked</emphasis> exception thrown at a matched join point, 
	      where the exception is an instance of the softened exception, will be softened to an 
	      <literal>org.aspectj.lang.SoftException</literal>. 
      </para>
      
       	<programlisting><![CDATA[
       	public aspect SoftenExample {
       	
       	  declare soft : Exception : execution(* Foo.*(..));
       	
       	}
       	
       	class Foo {
       	
       	  public static void main(String[] args) {
       	    Foo foo = new Foo();
       	    foo.foo();   
       	    foo.bar();
       	  }
       	
       	  void foo() throws Exception {
       	    throw new Exception();        // this will be converted to a SoftException
       	  }
       	  
       	  void bar() throws Exception {
       	    throw new RuntimeException();  // this will remain a RuntimeException
       	  }
       	
       	}
		]]></programlisting>
		
      
  </sect1>
  

</chapter>


