<chapter id="tools-intro" 
    xreflabel="Introduction to the AspectJ tools">
    <title>Introduction to the AspectJ tools</title>
<sect1 
	id="eclipse-aspectj"
	xreflabel="The Eclipse AspectJ implementation">
	<title>The Eclipse AspectJ implementation</title>
    <para>The <ulink url="../progguide/index.html">AspectJ Programming Guide</ulink>
        describes the AspectJ language.  This guide describes the AspectJ
        tools produced by the AspectJ
        team on 
         <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/aspectj">http://eclipse.org/aspectj</ulink>.
        The AspectJ tools include
        - ajc, the compiler/weaver;
        ajdoc, a documentation tool; ajbrowser, a crosscutting code viewer;
        Ant support for ajc; and load-time weaving support.
        These tools are delivered in the library folder of the AspectJ tools
        installation, mainly in <literal>aspectjtools.jar</literal> (tools) and
        <literal>aspectjrt.jar</literal> (runtime).
        This guide does not describe the Eclipse AspectJ development tools
        (AJDT).  That is produced by another team (sharing some members) on
         <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/aspectj">http://eclipse.org/ajdt</ulink>.
        AJDT is delivered as an Eclipse plugin, incorporating the classes in
        the AspectJ tools libraries along with the Eclipse plugin interface
        classes.
       </para>
    <para>
        Since AspectJ 1.1, the tools have implemented the AspectJ language 
        using bytecode weaving, which combines aspects and classes to produce
        .class files that run in a Java VM.  There are other ways to implement the
        language (e.g., compiler preprocessor, VM support); the AspectJ team
        has always tried to distinguish the language and the implementation
        so other groups could build alternative implementations of AspectJ.
        To that end,
         
    <ulink url="../progguide/implementation.html">The AspectJ Programming Guide,
    Implementation Notes</ulink> describes how the Java bytecode form affects
        language semantics.  VM- or source-based implementations may be free
        of these limits or impose limits of their own, but most should be
        fairly close to what's possible in Java bytecode.
    </para>
    <para> 
        Please be careful not to confuse any description of
        weaving or of this implementation of the AspectJ language with
        the AspectJ language semantics.
        If you do, you might find yourself writing code that doesn't work as
        expected when you compile or run it on other systems.  
        More importantly, if you
        think about aspects in terms of weaving or of inserting or merging
        code, then you can lose many of the design benefits of thinking
        about an aspect as a single crosscutting module. 
        When the text below introduces an implementation detail, it will warn if
        users make mistakes by applying it in lieu of the language semantics.
    </para>
</sect1>
    <!-- graphic for bytecode weaving -->
<sect1 
	id="bytecode-concepts"
	xreflabel="Bytecode weaving, incremental compilation, and memory usage">
	<title>Bytecode weaving, incremental compilation, and memory usage</title>
    <para>Bytecode weaving takes classes and aspects in .class form
        and weaves them together to produce binary-compatible .class files that 
        run in any Java VM and implement the AspectJ semantics.
        This process supports not only the compiler but also IDE's.
        The compiler, given an aspect in source form, produces a binary
        aspect and runs the weaver.  IDE's can get information about
        crosscutting in the program by subscribing to information 
        produced by weaver as a side-effect of weaving.
    </para>
    <para>Incremental compilation involves recompiling only what is necessary
        to bring the binary form of a program up-to-date with the source form
        in the shortest time possible.
        Incremental weaving supports this by weaving on a per-class basis.
        (Some implementations of AOP (including AspectJ 1.0) make use
        of whole-program analysis that can't be done in incremental mode.)
        Weaving per-class means that if the source for a pure Java class 
        is updated, only that class needs to be produced.  However, if
        some crosscutting specification may have been updated, then all
        code potentially affected by it may need to be woven.  The AspectJ
        tools are getting better at minimizing this effect, but it is to
        some degree unavoidable due to the crosscutting semantics.
    </para>
    <para>
        Memory usage can seem higher with AspectJ tools.
        Some aspects are written to potentially affect many classes, so each
        class must be checked during the process of weaving.  Programmers can
        minimize this by writing the crosscutting specifications as narrowly
        as possible while maintaining correctness.
        (While it may seem like more memory, the proper comparison
        would with with a Java program that had the same crosscutting,
        with changes made to each code segment.  That would likely require
        more memory and more time to recompile than the corresponding 
        AspectJ program.)
    </para>
<sect2 
	id="classpathInpathAndAspectpath"
	xreflabel="Classpath, inpath, and aspectpath">
	<title>Classpath, inpath, and aspectpath</title>
    <para>AspectJ introduces two new paths for the binary input to the
        weaver which you'll find referenced in <xref linkend="ajc-ref"/>,
        <xref linkend="ajbrowser"/>, 
        <xref linkend="antTasks"/>,
        and <xref linkend="ltw"/>.
    </para>
    <para>As in Java, the <literal>classpath</literal> is where the AspectJ
        tools resolve types specified in the program. When running an AspectJ
        program, the classpath should contain the classes and aspects along with
        the AspectJ runtime library, <literal>aspectjrt.jar</literal>.
        </para>
    <para>
        In AspectJ tools, the <literal>aspectpath</literal> is where to find binary
        aspects.  Like the classpath, it can include archives (.jar and .zip files) 
        and directories containing .class files in a package layout (since 
        binary aspects are in .class files).  These aspects affect other
        classes in exactly the same way as source-level aspects, but are themselves
        not affected.  When deploying programs, the original aspects must be included 
        on the runtime classpath.
    </para>
    <para>
        In AspectJ tools, the <literal>inpath</literal> is where to find binary
        input - aspects and classes that weave and may be woven.  
        Like the classpath, it can include archives and class directories. 
        Like the aspectpath, it can include aspects that affect other classes
        and aspects.
        However, unlike the aspectpath, an aspect on the inpath may itself be
        affected by aspects, as if the source were all compiled together.
        When deploying aspects that were put on the inpath, only the woven output 
        should be on the runtime classpath.
    </para>
    <para>
        Although types in the inpath and the aspectpath need to be resolved by
        the AspectJ tools, you usually do not need to place them on the classpath
        because this is done automatically by the compiler/weaver.  But when using 
        the <literal>WeavingURLClassLoader</literal>, your code must explicitly add the aspects
        to the classpath so they can be resolved (as you'll see in the sample
        code and the <literal>aj.bat</literal> script).
    </para>
    <para>The most common mistake is failing to add
        <literal>aspectjrt.jar</literal> to the classpath. Also, when
        weaving with binary aspects, users forget to deploy the aspect itself
        along with any classes it requires. A more subtle mistake is putting a
        binary aspect (BA) on the inpath instead of the aspectpath.  In this case
        the aspect BA might be affected by an aspect, even itself; this can 
        cause the program to fail, e.g., when an aspect uses exclusion to 
        avoid infinite recursion but fails to exclude advice in aspect BA.
        </para>
        <para>The latter is one of many ways that mistakes in the build process
            can affect aspects that are written poorly.  Aspects should never
            rely on the boundaries of the build specification to narrow the
            scope of their crosscutting, since the build can be changed 
            without notice to the aspect developer.  Careful users might even
            avoid relying on the implementation scope, to ensure their
            AspectJ code will run on other implementations.
        </para>
	</sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>